<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-14T12:19:57+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Publication accepted in PRD 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2025/article-hyperlsw/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Publication accepted in PRD 🎉"/><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2025/article-hyperlsw</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2025/article-hyperlsw/"><![CDATA[<p>Today, <a href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-hyperlsw">our recent preprint</a> got accepted for publication in the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevD.111.015003">Physical Review D</a>!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publications"/><category term="article,"/><category term="publication,"/><category term="result"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The future of light-shining-through-walls experiments]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New preprint on the arXiv 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-ksvz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New preprint on the arXiv 🎉"/><published>2024-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-ksvz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-ksvz/"><![CDATA[<p>As an early Christmas present, please consider reading our new preprint <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04772">on the arXiv</a>. Collaborating with my former MSc student and teo other researchers in Amsterdam and Padua, we took a closer look at our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.12378">model catalogue of axion models</a> in light of a recent observation that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16087">axion models can imply an alternative cosmological history</a>. As a result, we find “model islands” below the usual axion window and, in case of a discovery, the catalogue might prove invaluable for identifying the observed axion model.</p> <p>In the spirit of AxiTools, we made the models and some auxiliary material available <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14524493">on Zenodo</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication"/><category term="preprint,"/><category term="result"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New insights into cosmologically viable axion models]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Language Certificate Awarded 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/certificate_cils/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Language Certificate Awarded 🎉"/><published>2024-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/certificate_cils</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/certificate_cils/"><![CDATA[<p>Building soft skills is an integral part of the MSCA programme. One of my goals during the two years in Padua was to learn Italian, taking advantage of the free language courses offered by the University during the semester. After sitting the five-hour CILS (Certification of Italian as a Foreign Language) exam – and enduring a ridicolouly long wait of 3.5 months(!) for the results – I am happy to announce that I passed the exam at the C1 level!</p> <p>To put my newly acquired language skills to the test, here’s the Italian version of this blog post (hopefully without mistakes):</p> <p><em>Svillupare competenze trasversali fa parte del programma MSCA.</em> <em>Uno dei miei obiettivi durante i due anni a Padova era imparare italiano, approfittando dei corsi gratuiti offerti dall’Università durante il semestre.</em> <em>Dopo aver sostenuto l’esame CILS (Certificazione di Italiano come Lingua Straniera) di cinque ore &amp;ndash – e dopo aver atteso un periodo ridiculo di 3,5 mesi(!) per i risultati – annunciare di aver superato l’esame al livello C1!</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="award"/><category term="award"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AxiTools now speaks Italian at C1 level]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presentation at the IDM Conference</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/conf_idm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presentation at the IDM Conference"/><published>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/conf_idm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/conf_idm/"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I presented results from our upcoming work on “ultimate” future laboratory searches for axion-like particles (see the related blog post <a href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-hyperlsw">here</a>) at the <a href="https://www.idm2024.eu/">IDM 2024 conference</a>. The devastating 2009 earthquake destroyed much of the city of L’Aquila, so it is great to see that many of its buildings have been restored and filled again with life. During the conference, we also had the chance to visit the underground Gran Sasso National Laboratory, which hosts some of the most important <a href="https://www.lngs.infn.it/en/research">dark matter experiments</a> in the entire world. Needless to say that this made for a unique and insightful experience!</p> <p>The slides for my presentation can be found here <a href="https://agenda.infn.it/event/39713/contributions/233844/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="presentation"/><category term="conference,"/><category term="presentation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[L'Aquila, Italy]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New preprint on the arXiv 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-hyperlsw/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New preprint on the arXiv 🎉"/><published>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-hyperlsw</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-hyperlsw/"><![CDATA[<p>Today, my collaborators and I released a preprint on the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04772">arXiv preprint server</a>, disucssing the feasibility of future axion facilities in case of a discovery. We asked ourselves what the most ambitious laboratory experiments could achieve when using only currently available technology. This exercise provided important benchmarks for our ability to determine the axion’s properties and, in particular, to make robust statements about the amount of dark matter explained by them.</p> <p>It was a pleasure to collaborate with Joerg Jaeckel and Giuseppe Lucente from the University of Heidelberg (Germany) on this work!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication"/><category term="preprint,"/><category term="result"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The future of axion lab experiments]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Preprint on the arXiv 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-bhsr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Preprint on the arXiv 🎉"/><published>2024-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-bhsr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/preprint-bhsr/"><![CDATA[<p>Constraining extremely light axion-like particles is usually very difficult since their interaction strength with photons and matter typically decreases as their mass decreases. However, one fascinating way to exclude, or provide evidence for, the existence of such particles is via the process of black hole superradiance. The mere existence of a boson field around a black hole is sufficient to start extracting energy and spin from the black hole and grow a cloud of bosons around it. This effect is in contradiction to observing fast-spinning black holes, which can be used to derive constraints on the boson mass.</p> <p>In our new preprint <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10337">[arXiv:2406.10337]</a>, we explore how to improve the statistical analysis of obtaining such constraints: first, by doing a more rigorous analysis and, second, by proposing a method that can extract more information from future black hole data analyses.</p> <p>In the spirit of the AxiTools project, the accompanying code for our analysis is publicly available on <a href="https://github.com/sebhoof/bhsr">Github</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication"/><category term="preprint,"/><category term="result"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Improving how we analyse black hole superradiance]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Premio Asimov Awarded</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/premio_asimov/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Premio Asimov Awarded"/><published>2024-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/premio_asimov</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/premio_asimov/"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the outreach for the MSCA programme, I acted as a juror for the <em>Premio Asimov</em> award panel. The <em>Premio Asimov</em> is one of the most prestigious awards for popular science books in the Italian language. This edition’s award went to professor Giovanni Covone for his book <em>Altre Terre: Viaggio alla scoperta di pianeti extrasolari</em> (HarperCollins Italia), which lets the reader explore the research into exoplanets and their potential importance for the future of the human species.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="outreach"/><category term="award"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Prestigious Italian outreach award goes to Giovanni Covone]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seminar at LPTHE, Paris</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_paris/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seminar at LPTHE, Paris"/><published>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_paris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_paris/"><![CDATA[<p>On 5 April, I presented an overview of the work activities of the action in the “Particles &amp; Cosmology” seminar series hosted by the Laboratoire de Physique Théorique et Hautes Énergies (LPTHE) in Paris. My talk, titled “Finding Axions in a Universe of Data and Envisioning Their Use as Multi-Messenger Probes,” explored the exciting role of axions as both a theoretical puzzle and a practical tool for exploring the cosmos.</p> <p>Many thanks to the group leader for the opportunity to present my workand for the hospitality!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="presentation"/><category term="presentation,"/><category term="seminar"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Finding axions in a universe of data]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seminar at Nikhef, Amsterdam</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_nikhef/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seminar at Nikhef, Amsterdam"/><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_nikhef</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2024/seminar_nikhef/"><![CDATA[<p>On 25 January, I had the pleasure of presenting a seminar for the Nikhef Theory Group in Amsterdam. My talk, titled “Tools for Axion Model Predictions and Prospects for Their Detection in Astrophysics,” explored the exciting potential of axions as a cornerstone in our understanding of fundamental physics.</p> <p>If you’re interested in the background material, here are related arXiv links: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.07192">[arXiv:1810.07192]</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.08789">[arXiv:2101.08789]</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.12378">[arXiv:2107.12378]</a>, and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.00077">[arXiv:2306.00077]</a>. These works highlight some of my contributions to the tools and methodologies that enable precise predictions for axion models, as well as their implications for astrophysical observations.</p> <p>Many thanks to the Nikhef Theory Group for the invitation and their hospitality!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="presentation"/><category term="presentation,"/><category term="seminar"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tools for axion model predictions and astrophysical detection prospects]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computing Grant 🎉</title><link href="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2023/grant-iscra_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computing Grant 🎉"/><published>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2023/grant-iscra_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sebhoof.github.io/blog/2023/grant-iscra_2/"><![CDATA[<p>The MSCA project “AxiTools” was awarded high-performance computing time from the Italian SuperComputing Resource Allocation (<a href="https://www.hpc.cineca.it/hpc-access/access-cineca-resources/iscra-projects/">ISCRA</a>) scheme. I will conduct a “Class C” project on the GALILEO100 cluster to learn more about axions from string theory. Stay tuned for results!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hpc"/><category term="hpc,"/><category term="software"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ISCRA "Class C" project]]></summary></entry></feed>